[SPEAKER_03]: So, based on what we discussed just now, what would be the difference between the three types of practitioners, quote-unquote, that the siddhas talk about?
[SPEAKER_03]: And how would you practically... how would that practically manifest somebody's day-to-day?
[SPEAKER_03]: So, there's faith type, samādhi type, and wisdom type, as you would call it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, maybe one difference between the faith type and the wisdom type will be like the faith kind of understood to some degree some sort of instruction and you just stick to it kind of regardless of what his mind shouts at him.
[SPEAKER_00]: To kind of refine this understanding, you just keep to it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, like the wisdom type will have kind of tendency to try to dig more like what does it actually mean and how refined I should be doing that.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, does that mean that... is there any... would there be any fixed characteristic of, like, pleasant or unpleasant for one of them?
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah, I was kind of going to say, maybe they would almost be characterized by the dominating hindrances, basically.
[SPEAKER_03]: Well, both of those, yeah, would be mainly characterized by their... by the hindrances, yeah.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, like... Well, probably the sādhi would be the most pleasant.
[SPEAKER_04]: That's also what it's...
[SPEAKER_03]: So, basically, faith type and wisdom type, it wouldn't... it could be pleasant or unpleasant.
[SPEAKER_03]: Probably, it would be unpleasant.
[SPEAKER_03]: Because having faith doesn't necessarily mean that they are not acting out of hindrances.
[SPEAKER_03]: You can be having faith and still be, you know, inclining more towards the direction of engagement in other ways.
[SPEAKER_03]: Whereas the wisdom type would be inclining probably towards engagement in the form of overthinking things.
[SPEAKER_03]: So...
[SPEAKER_03]: That means then that...
[SPEAKER_03]: So, what would they each have to do?
[SPEAKER_02]: Well, wasting time.
[SPEAKER_02]: That's it.
[SPEAKER_02]: Refraining from trying to clarify things.
[SPEAKER_02]: On their own terms, let's say, like the thoughts or doubts they would present, like...
[SPEAKER_03]: But is that where they would begin?
[SPEAKER_03]: Excuse me?
[SPEAKER_03]: Is that where they would begin?
[SPEAKER_02]: Begin?
[SPEAKER_02]: What, the training?
[SPEAKER_03]: Yeah, begin the kind of rebalancing of their efforts.
[SPEAKER_02]: I'm not sure I understand what you're saying.
[SPEAKER_03]: Like, is that the first point where the restraint begins?
[SPEAKER_02]: No, obviously, the precepts.
[SPEAKER_03]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, we could see the wisdom in and of itself, even if they're not aware of it, would come with the implication that if I can just understand this...
[SPEAKER_02]: Right, okay.
[SPEAKER_02]: It doesn't matter so much... Yeah, yeah, yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: No, no, no.
[SPEAKER_02]: Of course.
[SPEAKER_02]: The stuff that... Yeah, unless you have perfected the precepts and
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah, but the thing is, like, still, more often than not, there would need to... there would be a need to refine their understanding of what that training means.
[SPEAKER_03]: Especially if they... since they will see that the practice is still being unpleasant,
[SPEAKER_03]: And they're not clear why.
[SPEAKER_03]: It's not that, like, they're knowingly kind of... there is some external reason because of which they're engaging, and they know that once that finishes, they'll go back.
[SPEAKER_03]: No, it's like, even if they wanted the practice not to be unpleasant, they don't know how.
[SPEAKER_03]: Well, that means, probably,
[SPEAKER_03]: If they think they're keeping all these prerequisites, then they probably need to refine their conception of what it means to be sensory trained, what it means to be not giving in to unwholesome states, what it means to be in seclusion, all these things.
[SPEAKER_03]: And their task would be then to
[SPEAKER_03]: Rebalance themselves and, like I was saying before, create the suitable basis for all these ideas to be seen on the level where they need to be seen, which is a mind that has been, again, de-agitated on account of renunciation, not on account of something else.
[SPEAKER_03]: Now, what would the samādhi type have to do?
[SPEAKER_03]: What would be their setback?
[SPEAKER_02]: Kind of laziness, I guess.
[SPEAKER_02]: Laziness?
[SPEAKER_02]: Well, indulging, I guess, if you could say, in that.
[SPEAKER_03]: But can you indulge in a state of renunciation?
[SPEAKER_02]: Well, no, I mean more like kind of relaxing, let's say.
[SPEAKER_03]: Is it that they need to give up the samādhi, as some people would think?
[SPEAKER_02]: No.
[SPEAKER_02]: But they would need to bring up, maybe, things to think about.
[SPEAKER_02]: That.
[SPEAKER_03]: Well, that too, but what more specifically would be, like, what is it that a patujana can become?
[SPEAKER_03]: Like, I mean, the Buddhist teachers reaching, like, the final arūpa attainments.
[SPEAKER_03]: Like, just the limit of where self-view goes.
[SPEAKER_03]: Like, if just one more, he would have been extinguished.
[SPEAKER_03]: So,
[SPEAKER_03]: Why is it that... whereas a sotāpanna, who actually understands, he might not even be, like, even in the first jhāna.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, why is it that there can be that huge discrepancy?
[SPEAKER_00]: What does... Because he's still delighting in his attainment and to learn how to relinquish that.
[SPEAKER_03]: But is it like a conscious, like, kind of
[SPEAKER_03]: Sensual delay, like it's usually happening with with the absorption states that people develop, or...
[SPEAKER_03]: Of course, there is the light for anybody who hasn't freed themselves from craving, but when you say it that way, it would almost sound like it's a very obvious sort of infatuation with it or something.
[SPEAKER_03]: But the thing is, you get there by giving up this coarse kind of intoxication with anything.
[SPEAKER_02]: Well, I guess, maybe, you know, you're taking that for a grant.
[SPEAKER_02]: You're taking that state to be your result, to be your goal.
[SPEAKER_02]: Goal of the grant.
[SPEAKER_02]: Take it to be yours.
[SPEAKER_03]: Yeah, but, okay, but, sure, those are broader kind of, uh...
[SPEAKER_03]: Like, in theoretical terms, but more specifically, like, what is it that they're not seeing?
[SPEAKER_03]: Basically, let's put it that way.
[SPEAKER_03]: Yeah, so you're asking, what is it that... What is it that the bhutujana, who has, like, more samādhi than an arahant, what is it that he doesn't see?
[SPEAKER_03]: What is the kind of small implication that they will still carry, no matter how
[SPEAKER_03]: Kind of deeply they go in that direction.
[SPEAKER_02]: Interact to that thing.
[SPEAKER_02]: You mean?
[SPEAKER_04]: In general, just what's the wrong assumption?
[SPEAKER_03]: Yeah, it's the self you, which is the... Yeah, of course, but what... how would that practically manifest, like in that specific example?
[SPEAKER_03]: Do you think that you could have somebody who has cultivated samādhi, and they know that there is no self?
[SPEAKER_03]: Do you think that would automatically make them be an arahant?
[SPEAKER_03]: Well, I don't know.
[SPEAKER_03]: Because you could just take in this information and then see like, oh yeah, yeah, of course, I already knew that.
[SPEAKER_04]: Yeah, but assuming that that whole yoniso development has been there, because otherwise they wouldn't be having that samādhi to begin with.
[SPEAKER_03]: Yeah, I know, but okay, let's say, let's put it this way.
[SPEAKER_03]: Imagine you meet that kind of person.
[SPEAKER_03]: Like, eh, like, they have been on account of some wrong view, like in the Buddha's time, some fire worshipper or something like that, or some Brahma...
[SPEAKER_02]: They're living perfectly straight.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah, yeah.
[SPEAKER_03]: More than an arahant.
[SPEAKER_03]: Like, more secluded, more withdrawn than an arahant.
[SPEAKER_03]: What kind of instruction would you give them for them to actually, kind of... Well, that they haven't escaped the realms of earth, basically.
[SPEAKER_04]: Okay, but what does that mean?
[SPEAKER_04]: Well, that they haven't fundamentally uprooted being.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, okay.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's still an activity.
[SPEAKER_00]: Like, still... kind of a jhāna is still volitionally produced, so they still kind of rely on some sort of... very subtle, of course, but still an activity.
[SPEAKER_03]: Uh-huh, okay.
[SPEAKER_03]: But how do they stop doing that?
[SPEAKER_00]: Do they just... okay, I'm not gonna... No, they need to contemplate that any activity is a burden.
[SPEAKER_00]: Like, any form of activity, regardless of the...
[SPEAKER_00]: All subtleties, regardless, like the whole picture, it is kind of a building, regardless.
[SPEAKER_04]: And what would be the goal of that discernment?
[SPEAKER_04]: Non-attachment to the pleasure, even of those states.
[SPEAKER_04]: And?
[SPEAKER_04]: Then it's done.
[SPEAKER_03]: Okay, but what other... See, the thing is, there's something more specific there, that is problematic.
[SPEAKER_03]: Something that they wouldn't be seeing.
[SPEAKER_04]: Some of you go all the way to, what is it, neither perception or non-perception, but aspetujana.
[SPEAKER_04]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_04]: And now you're asking, what is it that they are not seeing?
[SPEAKER_00]: That they can get something.
[SPEAKER_03]: Yeah, but what... What is it that, like, what is it that's... What is it that they take for granted, let's say?
[SPEAKER_01]: Let's phrase it this way.
[SPEAKER_02]: Why is it that
[SPEAKER_03]: The fetter of sīla-bhāta-paramāsa wouldn't be overcome in the... because sīla-bhāta-paramāsa doesn't just mean the rites and rituals that we often say.
[SPEAKER_03]: It's the right virtue, the right duties of being secluded, you know, restraining your speech and all this stuff, that would factually lead to this peaceful states.
[SPEAKER_00]: Is it like, I have to do it?
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, but like...
[SPEAKER_00]: I have to keep those things.
[SPEAKER_00]: I have to engage.
[SPEAKER_03]: The thing is, if you just, like, if you just tell... stop thinking, I am this, like...
[SPEAKER_03]: They can easily, they can easily, kind of, oh, yeah, yeah, yeah, okay, okay.
[SPEAKER_03]: Because, see, they have already developed a degree of giving up.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, it's like, they can even think that that's what they're already doing.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, you have to phrase it in more accurate terms that would, like, directly cut through their assumption and the thing that they're emphasizing.
[SPEAKER_03]: And I think I actually already mentioned it a few times, but it seems it didn't fully make the connection between...
[SPEAKER_00]: Is it to make them recognize that this state is, like, dependently arisen?
[SPEAKER_03]: Yeah, but, like, let's say, let's not put the emphasis on the states.
[SPEAKER_03]: Let's, let's say, um... How they are living their lives.
[SPEAKER_04]: No, no, no, no, no, no.
[SPEAKER_02]: Right, right, right.
[SPEAKER_02]: That even this state that they have developed is dependent on this lifestyle.
[SPEAKER_02]: That taking for granted the
[SPEAKER_04]: Yes, that would bring them closer to you.
[SPEAKER_03]: Yeah, well, they see impermanence in regard to everything else except this.
[SPEAKER_03]: Like, they have reached that state by seeing the impermanence of
[SPEAKER_03]: Sensual pleasures... because the suttas describe these aesthetics, not during the Buddha's time, but before.
[SPEAKER_03]: They would factually reach the Brahman realm and so on, because they developed the understanding of sensuality as impermanent.
[SPEAKER_03]: They would be preaching that as their dhamma, but it would stop there.
[SPEAKER_03]: They would see the impermanence of that too, but now
[SPEAKER_03]: The point is, like, sure, that's just an answer that somebody can read the sutta and they just say, oh, yeah, they need to see that state, too, as impermanent.
[SPEAKER_03]: But what I'm saying is, what is it that you could point them to, to, like, really make sure that their understanding is impermanent?
[SPEAKER_03]: Because, again, they could just assimilate that view and say, oh, yeah, yeah, yeah, okay, yeah, of course, it's impermanent, because... Yeah, so then it stays on the level of information.
[SPEAKER_03]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, how could... how would you tell them, like, if you understood it as impermanent, if you actually understood it as impermanent, what would happen?
[SPEAKER_04]: There would be complete dispassion.
[SPEAKER_03]: Which would mean that?
[SPEAKER_03]: Exactly.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, that's what I was trying to get to.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, like, they would still be carrying the implication that, even if they think they're free from suffering, because the sutta would say, like, Bahía and stuff, he was exactly in that position where he was.
[SPEAKER_03]: It's probably unthinkable that he would have been thinking that, unless he had developed his mind in these ways.
[SPEAKER_03]: But, eh...
[SPEAKER_03]: Yeah, unless they recognize that actually it doesn't matter.
[SPEAKER_03]: Because you can have all the views of like, oh, yeah, it's impermanent and it's like this and it's like that.
[SPEAKER_03]: But as long as there's that implication that only if I have this,
[SPEAKER_03]: Will I be in the right kind of position?
[SPEAKER_03]: Will I be practicing rightly?
[SPEAKER_03]: To that extent, you haven't understood that this is not worth holding on to, and it's not where the purity comes from.
[SPEAKER_03]: And for as long as that's the case, you will also have seen a lot of paramāsa.
[SPEAKER_03]: Because your peace will depend, like you said, on the lifestyle that produced... that enables the state.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, it's not that that virtue that they were keeping, that would give rise to this, was wrong, and they should stop doing it.
[SPEAKER_03]: It's the fact that if they recognize that a peaceful mind isn't what... isn't what freedom from suffering is, isn't what nibbāna is, if they weren't to understand that,
[SPEAKER_03]: They would keep the virtue with a completely different attitude.
[SPEAKER_03]: They would keep the virtue without any fear of what would happen if they don't keep the virtue, because they're not afraid of the agitated mind.
[SPEAKER_03]: But, if their notion of peace is intrinsically bound up with this pure state that they have cultivated, inevitably, they will be afraid
[SPEAKER_03]: of what will happen if they give up all of the right training that they've been cultivating, and, let's say, not fully start engaging in sensuality or something, but just go back to a precepts and live in a crowded environment, which, again, an arahant could also do, if there's some reason for it or some accident or something, and they just can't live in the monastery anymore.
[SPEAKER_03]: Like, if this
[SPEAKER_03]: But the problem is, like, nowadays, these ideas are so, kind of,
[SPEAKER_03]: When the Buddha said that, it was revolutionary.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, like, somebody hears that, and they would be forced to think about it.
[SPEAKER_03]: It's like, oh, yeah, what... huh, what does he mean with that?
[SPEAKER_03]: But nowadays, you just say to someone, and whoever has any inkling of spirituality would have heard that before.
[SPEAKER_03]: And they would just say... they might even have cultivated the state by practicing something like that.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, they will think, like, oh, yeah, of course, yeah, yeah, of course, it's the pen.
[SPEAKER_03]: But no, it's like, accurately speaking, if you were to actually understand that, then why... Because then you would realize, actually, sometimes, I'm even prioritizing things that are necessary for this karma to come about, but are not fully indispensable to be free from veda, vision, and delusion.
[SPEAKER_03]: Like avoiding all talk, avoiding all speech.
[SPEAKER_03]: The Buddha didn't do that.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, avoiding criticizing others, because that would probably... and avoiding discussions and kind of engaging in in-depth conversations about dhamma.
[SPEAKER_03]: The Buddha didn't avoid those things, because he understood that
[SPEAKER_03]: Even when the mind would get slightly, kind of, fall back, basically, from the state of samādhi, that depends on seclusion, he wouldn't suffer on account of this.
[SPEAKER_03]: But somebody whose sense of identity, literally, depends on having that withdrawn mind all the time, they would feel like, oh, yeah, I always need to be living this super tight lifestyle of
[SPEAKER_03]: Not just, again, the precepts, but, like, all of these other layers of withdrawal added to it.
[SPEAKER_03]: So... and that's why, then, the Buddha told Mahākassapa that... oh, just... just come back.
[SPEAKER_03]: And live in the palace, because you don't need, you don't need the seclusion and the, like, living in that cave where he was, that he had to, like, walk up.
[SPEAKER_04]: Your job is done.
[SPEAKER_03]: Yeah, he had to, like, walk up this, this huge hill just to reach that cave where he was living, like, completely withdrawn from, from people.
[SPEAKER_03]: And then he said it's, it's for the example, to give a good example to next generations.
[SPEAKER_03]: And for his pleasant abiding here and now, that he would continue to do it, because he realized, oh yeah, inevitably, even being an arahant, if we were to go back to that more engaged lifestyle, meeting people all the time and all this stuff, that pleasant abiding would deteriorate.
[SPEAKER_03]: But see, it didn't say like, oh, I won't do it because I need this.
[SPEAKER_04]: No.
[SPEAKER_04]: So, in his case, it was just a preference.
[SPEAKER_03]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_03]: But...
[SPEAKER_03]: But if, for some reason, he got sick, and he had to not live up there anymore, and just live in a more crowded place, he wouldn't suffer, even if then his samādhi deteriorated.
[SPEAKER_04]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_04]: So, there's basically... and it also... so, there would be no fear, as you mentioned earlier.
[SPEAKER_04]: And that sometimes, indeed, also the suttas say, like, free from greed, hatred, and illusion, and fear.
[SPEAKER_03]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_03]: So... because if there's anything that you hold on to, even if it's the things that are beneficial for the practice, to that extent you will suffer.
[SPEAKER_03]: It's a better attachment than all the others, because this one is... takes you closer to nibbāna rather than away from it, but if you just stay there, it's kind of like... kind of like... you just move all the way to, like, the crossing point.
[SPEAKER_03]: And then you stay there.
[SPEAKER_03]: You could have just... but no.
[SPEAKER_03]: You stay there.
[SPEAKER_03]: And then you die.
[SPEAKER_03]: And I guess nobody tells you like, wait, wait, no, no.
[SPEAKER_03]: Just one step more.
[SPEAKER_03]: Don't stop.
[SPEAKER_03]: Then, yeah, there's no indication that you're not suffering anymore.
[SPEAKER_03]: So why?
[SPEAKER_03]: Why would you keep trying to do anything more?
[SPEAKER_02]: But so, there's this sutta, I think it's in Utah somewhere, there's this sick monk, basically dying, I think, and the Buddha comes and he asks him how he's doing.
[SPEAKER_02]: He's like, yeah, I'm not doing very well.
[SPEAKER_02]: And he says, ah, okay, well, I hope you're at least free from remorse.
[SPEAKER_02]: And I said, no, no, no, I'm not free from remorse.
[SPEAKER_03]: And he said, why?
[SPEAKER_02]: Well, because I fell away from the thing.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, are you saying that the monk did not even have the right view?
[SPEAKER_02]: Or could someone with the right view
[SPEAKER_03]: No, there could still be, there could still be, there could still be some slight emphasis of, like, that only when it's, when it's... because there's still conceit and kind of identification with the aggregates, so they could still have a sense that, that they need to have.
[SPEAKER_02]: Of course, they would see through it.
[SPEAKER_03]: Eventually, that's the difference.
[SPEAKER_03]: If they were just to practice long enough, it would become clear that they have to apply the same principle of
[SPEAKER_03]: They just wouldn't be able to hold on to it, to anywhere near the same degree, as somebody who doesn't have the right view.
[SPEAKER_03]: But yeah, that's why it does say that once they develop it well enough, then they do contemplate that that's also impermanent and all that.
[SPEAKER_03]: Not because they are, like the other person, implying that it's actually eternal.
[SPEAKER_03]: Like those Brahmas, they would actually have the view that, like, no, this is... kind of, eh... overdoing the... the... kind of, eh...
[SPEAKER_03]: Finding safety in it.
[SPEAKER_03]: They know that there is, like I say, somebody accomplishes a view, is incapable of taking any saṅkhara as permanent, any saṅkhara as pleasant, and any dhamma as self.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, they cannot have the view that it's otherwise.
[SPEAKER_03]: But there can still be, just by not being fully clear,
[SPEAKER_03]: That it's like, not just impermanent, but as it says, it's like a dart, a boil, an arrow.
[SPEAKER_03]: It's a calamity, a disaster.
[SPEAKER_03]: Then, they aren't fully... they aren't fully turned away from the entire extent of the aggregates, basically.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, back to your question of what does a... well, a faith type and a wisdom type and a samādhi type, what do they have to do in order to overcome the... Shortcomings.
[SPEAKER_01]: Corresponding shortcomings, yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: Would a sort of simple answer to that be to try to understand what the other two types are and to try to emulate them?
[SPEAKER_03]: In a way, that could be a good way to look at it.
[SPEAKER_03]: Because, yeah, it would be like...
[SPEAKER_03]: If, actually, no, there's even that sutra where it says somebody who is accomplished in
[SPEAKER_03]: Discernment should go and ask somebody who is accomplished in calming.
[SPEAKER_03]: Somebody who is accomplished in discernment should go and ask somebody.
[SPEAKER_03]: It says, how should you regard saṅkharas, in order to develop discernment, basically.
[SPEAKER_03]: And so, that would be...
[SPEAKER_03]: Yeah, that would be the way to kind of fill out the things that they haven't sufficiently cultivated.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, in the case of the wizard type, yeah, it would just be like, okay, how do I kind of keep myself in check not to drift away into some sort of random distractions, even if they seem justified, of like thinking about dhamma and stuff.
[SPEAKER_03]: Or the faith type distractions of, who knows, like helping the teacher or something, just overly kind of like, oh, let me take care of this.
[SPEAKER_03]: Do you want me to renew the hokuti?
[SPEAKER_03]: Do you want a new bathroom?
[SPEAKER_03]: So, then, for the samādhi type, then it would just be like actively clarifying
[SPEAKER_03]: The nature of their experience in such a way that even when they're not at peace, they still wouldn't suffer.
[SPEAKER_03]: To kind of take away the emphasis from the peace and see, like, you know, how can I not suffer even amidst suffering, so that, you know, even if I were to just, again, completely, like, live in this crowded environment, in a hospital or something, that even then I wouldn't suffer.
[SPEAKER_03]: How could I... how could I see myself... how could I develop such understanding that I don't suffer even when I'm going around left and right like this other guy does?